A Finding Aid to the Kenyon and Louise Cox Papers, 1876-1977, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Kenyon and Louise Cox papers
1876-1977
Archives of American Art
Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919
AAA.coxkenyl
Archival Resource Key
0.3 Linear feet
The papers of Kenyon and Louise Cox measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1876 to 1977. Included are Kenyon and Louise's Certificate of Marriage, autobiographical notes by Louise focusing on her time at the National Academy of Design, writings, and correspondence, primarily from Kenyon Cox, including several illustrated letters. Also found is artwork by Kenyon and others, including Julian Alden Weir, biographical material on Jacob Dolson Cox, Keyon's Father, photographs and printed reproductions of artwork, magazine and newspaper clippings, an unpublished bibliography on Kenyon Cox, and a handwritten list of Kenyon Cox paintings in the National Academy of Design permanent collection.
Biographical Note
Kenyon Cox was a prominent American painter, lecturer, and art critic. He was born in 1856, in Warren, Ohio, and he studied painting at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and in Paris, where he befriended artist Augustus Saint-Gaudens. Cox returned to the United States and made a living illustrating magazines and books, and teaching at the Art Students League in New York. In 1892 he married his student Louise Howland King, born in San Francisco in 1865. Together they became prominent painters and were responsible for the murals that decorated the Liberal Arts Building at the 1893 Columbian Exposition in Chicago. During his career, Cox contributed articles and essays on art subjects to various magazines. He was a member of the Society of American Artists, the National Academy of Design, and the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Kenyon Cox died in 1919 and Louise in 1945. Their son, Allyn, born in 1896, became a successful muralist.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Kenyon and Louise Cox measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1876 to 1977. Included are Kenyon and Louise's Certificate of Marriage, autobiographical notes by Louise focusing on her time at the National Academy of Design, writings, and correspondence, primarily from Kenyon Cox, including several illustrated letters. Also found is artwork by Kenyon and others, including Julian Alden Weir, biographical material on Jacob Dolson Cox, Keyon's Father, photographs and printed reproductions of artwork, magazine and newspaper clippings, an unpublished bibliography on Kenyon Cox, and a handwritten list of Kenyon Cox paintings in the National Academy of Design permanent collection.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, items are categorized into one series. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Charles E. Feinberg, 1955-1968, the National Museum of American Art in 1967 and 1984, and the Cooper Hewitt Museum in 1983. The material was microfilmed upon receipt as two separate manuscript collections.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Allyn Cox papers, 1870-1982. His papers contain correspondence, biographies, photographs, sketchbooks, writings, and printed material, some of it relating to his father, Kenyon Cox.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of this collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Kenyon and Louise Cox were digitized in 2006 by the Archives of American Art, and total 168 images.
Photographs; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, American; Illustrated letters; Art critics; Works of art; Cox, Louise Howland King, 1865-1945
- Kenyon and Louise Cox papers, 1876-1977; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  - Certificate of Marriage, 1892; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1877; 1882; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Oversize material housed in OV 2
  - Correspondence, 1893-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autobiographical Notes by Louise Cox, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speech by Kenyon Cox, 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writings, "Artist and Public" by Kenyon Cox, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings, Miscellaneous, 1892; 1933; 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Drawings, 1876; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Material on Jacob Dolson Cox, circa 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1888-1922; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed Material, Reproductions of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1884-1977; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed Material, Miscellaneous, 1901-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bibliography on Kenyon Cox, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - List of Paintings by Kenyon Cox in the N.A.D. Permanent Collection, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oversize Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 2)
    Oversize material scanned with Box 1, Folder 2
  - Oversize Drawings, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 2)
    Oversize material scanned with Box 1, Folder 8
  - Oversize Printed Material, Reproductions of Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 2)
    Oversize material from Box 1, Folder 11
  - Oversize Printed Material, Clippings, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 2)
    Oversize material scanned with Box 1, Folder 12